<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2022-09-01T16:00:24+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Welcome to the personal website of Gaurav Gyawali, a PhD student at Cornell University. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Quantum Ergodic Theorem</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2022/QET/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantum Ergodic Theorem"/><published>2022-08-06T22:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-06T22:41:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2022/QET</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2022/QET/"><![CDATA[<p>We humans find great joy in being able to comprehend complex ideas in simple terms. Our sensory and intellectual faculties severely limit the range of our experiences as well as their understanding. Thus, the exercise of simplification enables us to see the beauty we’d not have seen otherwise. In this sense, statistical mechanics serves as a lens that enables us to appreciate incomprehensible microscopic complexity by bringing it to relatively simpler statistical terms that we are able to appreciate.</p> <p>It is common in statistical mechanics to describe the equilibrium behavior of a system of particles by using a statistical ensemble. For example, a microcanonical ensemble is used to describe an isolated system i.e. the one that doesn’t exchange energy or particles with the surrounding environment. Regardless of the initial state, such a system settles down to a typical state without the memory of where it began. A microcanonical ensemble is an equal probability distribution over a constant energy surface. For a system consisting of simple harmonic oscillators, we can think of a microcanonical ensemble as a spherical shell of thickness \(\delta E\) at a radius \(E\) from the center (see Fig. 1). In classical systems, ergodicity and Louiville’s theorem provide the link between the time-averaging and microcanonical averaging.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Microcanonical-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Microcanonical-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Microcanonical-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Microcanonical.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><em>Fig 1. A microcanonical ensemble i.e. a statistical description of an isolated system in equilibrium is defined as an equal probability distribution over a constant energy shell.</em></p> <p>In our statistical mechanics courses, we borrow the microcanonical idea, and apply it to isolated quantum systems. Nevertheless, we also learn that the dynamics of a quantum state \(\ket{\psi_0}\) is described by a unitary evolution i.e. \(\ket{\psi_t} = e^{\frac{-iHt}{\hbar}} \ket{\psi_0}\). A natural question then arises- how can a reversible process be described by a statistical ensemble that completely ignores the history of the state? John von Neuman, one of the founding father of quantum mecahnics, attempted to answer this question with his quantum ergodic theorem (QET) [1], the main topic of this article.</p> <p>Let’s start by introducing some notations. We use the density matrix formalism to describe the classical probability distributions of quantum wavefunctions. If the initial state belongs to a constant energy subspace \(\mathcal{H}\) of the Hilbert space \(\mathcal{H}_{total}\), then the resulting equilibrium state can be described by the microcanonical ensemble given by \begin{equation} \rho_{mc} = \frac{1}{D} \mathrm{I}_{D}, \end{equation} where \(D = \text{dim} (\mathcal{H})\). Notice how all the states in the constant energy subspace have equal classical probability of \(\frac{1}{D}\). Thus, the equilibrium expectation value of an observable \(O\) is</p> <p>\begin{equation} \langle O \rangle = \text{Tr}(\rho_{mc} O) = \frac{1}{D} \text{Tr}(O). \end{equation}</p> <p>When we say that a state is equivalent to a microcanonical ensemble, we mean it in the macroscopic sense. A macroscopic observable \(O\) partitions \(\mathcal{H}\) into ‘macro-spaces’ \(H_\nu\)’s such that (see Fig. 2 ): \begin{equation} \mathcal{H} = \bigoplus_\nu H_\nu. \end{equation} Two density matrices \(\rho\) and \(\rho'\) are said to be macroscopically equivalent (with respect to a macroscopic observable \(O\)) if and only if \begin{equation} \label{eqn:macroscopic_equivalence} \text{Tr}(\rho P_\nu) \approx \text{Tr}(\rho’ P_{\nu}), \end{equation} where \(P_\nu\)’s are the projections onto the \(d_\nu\) dimensional subspace \(H_\nu\). Thus, the macroscopic equivalence of \(\ket{\psi} \bra{\psi}\) and \(\rho_{mc}\) requires from Eqn \eqref{eqn:macroscopic_equivalence}: \begin{equation} \label{eqn:projection_dimension} \text{Tr}(\ket{\psi}\bra{\psi} P_\nu) \approx \text{Tr}(\rho_{mc} P_{\nu}) \implies |P_{\nu} \ket{\psi} |^2 \approx\frac{d_\nu}{D}, \end{equation} for all \(\nu\). A state \(\ket{\psi}\) that satisfies this property is called <em>normal</em>.</p> <p>The QET provides conditions under which a system is normal for every initial state vector \(\psi_0\). Consider a Hamiltonian \(H\) with non-degenerate energy levels \(E_0, E_1, \cdots, E_D\) as well as non-degenerate gaps i.e. \(E_m - E_n \neq E_m' - E_n'\), unless \(m=m'\) and \(m \neq m'\), or \(m=m'\) and \(n=n'\). QET states that such a system holds normal typicality with respect to most macroscopic observables for every initial wave function \(\ket{\psi_0} \in \mathcal{H}\) such that \(&lt;\psi_0|\psi_0&gt; =1\). In late 1950’s numerous papers dismissing the validity of QET appeared, and it was later realized that the papers were instead considering a weaker version of QET rather than von Neumann’s statement. One might ask- at what time does a state start being normal. QET doesn’t answer this question; von Neumann made noted that the equilibration time could be longer than the age of the universe. When a state reaches normal typicality, it is said to be thermalized. We note that thermalization is a stronger condition that equilibration. Equilibration means that we will be able to express time-averages with a diagonal ensemble[2] i.e.</p> <p>\begin{equation} \langle O \rangle_T = \frac{1}{T}\int_0^T dt \bra{\psi_t} O \ket{\psi_t} = \text{Tr}(O \rho_D), \end{equation}</p> <p>where \(\rho_D = \overline{\ket{\psi_t}\bra{\psi_t}}\). Thermalization requires an additional condition i.e.</p> <p>\begin{equation} \text{Tr}(O \rho_D) = \text{Tr}(O \rho_{mc}) = &lt;O_{mc}&gt;, \end{equation}</p> <p>which requires Eqn. \eqref{eqn:macroscopic_equivalence} to hold true.</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 480px)" srcset="/assets/img/Hilbert_space_partition-480.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 800px)" srcset="/assets/img/Hilbert_space_partition-800.webp"/> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" media="(max-width: 1400px)" srcset="/assets/img/Hilbert_space_partition-1400.webp"/> <img src="/assets/img/Hilbert_space_partition.png" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="500" height="auto" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p><em>Fig 2. A macroscopic observable \(O\) partitions the constant energy subspace \(\mathcal{H}\) into subspaces \(\{ \mathcal{H}_\nu \}\) such that \(\sum_\nu d_\nu =D\), where \(d_\nu = \text{dim} (\mathcal{H}_\nu)\), and \(D = \text{dim} (\mathcal{H})\).</em></p> <p>[1] John von Neumann. Proof of the ergodic theorem and the h-theorem in quantum mechanics. The European Physical Journal H, 35(2):201–237, 2010.</p> <p>[2] Masahito Ueda. Quantum equilibration, thermalization and prethermalization in ultracold atoms. Nature Reviews Physics, 2(12):669–681, 2020</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="scienceblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We humans find great joy in being able to comprehend complex ideas in simple terms. Our sensory and intellectual faculties severely limit the range of our experiences as well as their understanding. Thus, the exercise of simplification enables us to see the beauty we’d not have seen otherwise. In this sense, statistical mechanics serves as a lens that enables us to appreciate incomprehensible microscopic complexity by bringing it to relatively simpler statistical terms that we are able to appreciate.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Displaying External Posts on Your al-folio Blog"/><published>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-23T23:20:09+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2022/displaying-external-posts-on-your-al-folio-blog/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author></entry><entry><title type="html">Classical Shadow</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2021/Classical-Shadow/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Classical Shadow"/><published>2021-12-13T17:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-12-13T17:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2021/Classical-Shadow</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2021/Classical-Shadow/"><![CDATA[<p>Obtaining any useful information from a quantum computer requires performing measurement on the quantum state. Since the dimension of the Hilbert space increases exponentially in the number of qubits, a naive strategy to measure the expectation values involves exponentially large number of measurements. Huang et. al [1,2] have developed an approximate classical description of a quantum state using very few measurements on a quantum state, called the classical shadow, which allows us to accurately predict \(M\) different functions of the state with high success probability with just order \(log(M)\) measurements.</p> <p>The authors have also shown the effectiveness of this approach in machine-learning applications for quantum many-body problems.</p> <h2 id="definition">Definition</h2> <p>To construct a classical shadow representation, a unitary \(U\) chosen at random from a fixed ensemble, is used to rotate a quantum state \(\rho\) to \(U \rho U^\dagger\). Measurement on the computational basis is then performed which collapses \(\rho\) to \(U^\dagger \ket{\hat{b}} \bra{\hat{b}} U\) with probability \(\bra{\hat{b}} U \rho U^\dagger \ket{\hat{b}}\), where \(\hat{b} \in \{0,1\}^n\). The state \(U^\dagger \ket{\hat{b}} \bra{\hat{b}} U\) is a classical description of \(\rho\) that we can store in a classical memory, and its expectation value over both the unitary ensemble \(\mathcal{U}\) and outcomes \(b\) describes a quantum channel \(\rho \rightarrow \mathcal{M}(\rho)\): \(\label{measurement_channel} \mathrm{E} \left[ U^\dagger \ket{\hat{b}} \bra{\hat{b}} U \right] = \mathrm{E}_{U \in \: \mathcal{U}} \sum_{b \in\{0,1\}^{n}} \bra{b}U \rho U^{\dagger}\ket{b} U^{\dagger}\ket{b} \bra{b} U=\mathcal{M}(\rho).\)</p> <p>The ensemble \(\mathcal{U}\) is tomographically complete if for any given two states, we can always find some rotation which can distinguish between them. Tomographic completeness ensures the existence of a unique inverse \(\mathcal{M} ^{-1}\) and we can define \(\hat{\rho}=\mathcal{M}^{-1}\left(U^{\dagger}|\hat{b}\rangle\langle\hat{b}| U\right)\). The array \((\rho;N) = {\hat{\rho}_1, \cdots \hat{\rho}_N}\) is called the classical shadow of \(\rho\) with size \(N\). \(\hat{\rho}\) has a unit trace, but it is not necessarily positive semi-definite. Thus, it is not a physical density matrix although it reproduces $\rho$ in expectation i.e. \(\mathrm{E}[\hat{\rho}] = \rho\) in principle. In practice, we desire to predict various linear (eg. \(tr(O\rho)\)) as well as non linear (eg. \(tr(\rho \text{log}(\rho)\)) functions of \(\rho\), or predict its phase.</p> <h2 id="choice-of-unitary-ensembles">Choice of unitary ensembles</h2> <p>A practical realization of the above technique requires a unitary ensemble that allows us to predict the properties of a state \(\rho\), ideally with just a few copies. It is not surprising that the Clifford unitaries, which are ubiquitous in quantum information/computing, appear here as well. Huang et. al. [1] propose two kinds of unitary ensembles- i) random Clifford unitaries on the entire Hilbert space, ii) tensor products of random 2-qubit Clifford unitaries (or Pauli matrices). They show that predicting linear functions with error \(\epsilon\) requires at least \(\text{log}(M) \text{max}_i \text{tr}(O_i^2)/\epsilon^2\) and \(\text{log}(M)3^k \epsilon^2\) copies of the state \(\rho\) using random Clifford and random Pauli measurements respectively</p> <p>The authors also show that the classical shadow representation is capable of predicting nonlinear functions such as entanglement entropy, but the size of the classical shadow scales exponentially in the subsystem size.</p> <h2 id="machine-learning-application">Machine Learning Application</h2> <p>In Ref [2], Huang et. al. prove that the classical machine learning algorithms can efficiently predict the ground state properties of gapped Hamiltonians in finite spatial dimensions, after learning the classical shadows of other ground states in the same phase of matter. An interesting example is classifying the quantum phases of matter. Classifying the symmetry-breaking phases is conceptually simple because it involves calculating \(\text{tr}(\rho O)\), for some k-local observable $O$ such that \(\text{tr}(\rho O) \geq 1 \: \forall \: \rho \in \text{ phase A}\), and \(\text{tr}(\rho O) \leq -1 \: \forall \: \rho \in \text{ phase B}\).</p> <p>In contrast to the symmetry-breaking phases, topological phases cannot be distinguished by measuring some local observable \(O\). It involves measuring a nonlinear function of $\rho$, for example the entanglement entropy. Learning the nonlinear function requires a more expressive ML model. The authors thus devise a mapping from classical shadow \(S(\rho, N)\) to a highly expressive feature space that includes the polynomial expansion of many-body reduced density matrices. Using this feature space, they establish a rigorous guarantee that a classical ML can efficiently classify the topological phases of matter as well. The provided examples include the topological phases of the toric code and bond-alternating XXZ Hamiltonians.</p> <p>Classical shadow, thus, serves as an efficient yet powerful classical representation of a quantum state with a potential to play a key role in harnessing the NISQ devices for simulating many-body systems.</p> <h2 id="citations">Citations</h2> <p>[1] Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, and John Preskill. Predicting many prop- erties of a quantum system from very few measurements. Nature Physics, 16(10):1050–1057, Jun 2020.</p> <p>[2] Hsin-Yuan Huang, Richard Kueng, Giacomo Torlai, Victor V Albert, and John Preskill. Provably efficient machine learning for quantum many-body problems. arXiv preprint arXiv:2106.12627, 2021. 4</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="scienceblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Obtaining any useful information from a quantum computer requires performing measurement on the quantum state. Since the dimension of the Hilbert space increases exponentially in the number of qubits, a naive strategy to measure the expectation values involves exponentially large number of measurements. Huang et. al [1,2] have developed an approximate classical description of a quantum state using very few measurements on a quantum state, called the classical shadow, which allows us to accurately predict \(M\) different functions of the state with high success probability with just order \(log(M)\) measurements.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">दामनदेखि चन्द्रागिरीको यात्रा</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2021/Nepal-Travel/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="दामनदेखि चन्द्रागिरीको यात्रा"/><published>2021-10-24T17:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-10-24T17:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2021/Nepal-Travel</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2021/Nepal-Travel/"><![CDATA[<p>नेपाल आउँदा संजय सँग कुनै नयाँ ठाउँ मा घुम्न जाने सधैँ मेरो योजना मा पर्ने गर्छ। ऊ मेरो हाई स्कुल देखि को साथी हो र हामी एक अर्का सँग फिरन्ते पारा ले नयाँ ठाउँ मा जान रमाइलो मान्छौँ । बिगतका केहि नेपाल यात्रामा योजना हरु हुँदा हुँदै पनि ऊसँग घुम्न जाने मौका नमिलेको हुनाले हामीले अग्रीम योजना बनाउने काम गर्न छाड्यौँ । वास्तविकतामा परिणत नहुने योजना बुन्दै बस्नु बेकार छ, त्यसैले हामीले सँगै यात्रा गर्ने इच्छ्या लाई प्रबल राख्दै यसलाई भबिष्य को गर्व मै छाडी बस्यौँ। बिगतमा हामीले गरेका मुक्तिनाथ र पूनहिलका यात्राहरू अझै पनि स्मृति मा ताजा छन्, र तिनै स्मृतिले मलाई जीवनभरि यात्रा नै यात्रा गरिरहुँ जस्तो लाग्छ। नेपालका धेरै कुना काप्चा अनि विकट ठाउँहरूको यात्रा संजयले तय गरिसकेको छ। मेरो आजभोली को बसाईं अमेरिकातिर भएको हुनाले मैले नेपालको सोचेजति यात्रा गर्न पाएको छैन, तर मौका मिले सम्म अनि समयले भ्याए सम्म नेपाल आउँदा घुम्ने काममा म सधैं नै इच्छुक हुने गर्छु। भनिन्छ ज्ञान तीन किसिमका हुन्छन - सूतमय, चिन्तामय अनि भावमय। यी तीनमध्ये भावमय ज्ञान सर्वश्रेस्ठ मानिन्छ किनभने कुनै कुरा को देखाई र चिन्तनबाट जति ज्ञान प्राप्त गर्न सकिन्छ त्यो भन्दा धेरै गुणा ज्ञान त्यसको भोगाईबाट प्राप्त हुन्छ। मलाई बाल्यकालदेखि सुन्दै आएका अनि नसुनेका नेपालक दूरदराजका ठाउँहरू पुगेर त्यहाँका मानिस हरु ले गर्ने अनुभूति आफैँ गर्ने धोको छ। हुन त मा विदेशमा लामो समयदेखि बस्दै आएको मान्छे, नेपाल कै अनुभव किन गर्नु पर्यो? अमेरिका, युरोप मा पनि धेरैभन्दा धेरै प्राकृतिक सुन्दरताले युक्त ठाउँहरू छन् भन्ने प्रश्न उठ्न सक्छ। हो, मलाई यी ठाउँहरूको पनि येथेस्ट मात्रमा भ्रमण गर्ने इच्छ्या छ, तर त्यो भन्दा धेरै बढि मलाई आफू यहाँका पर्वत, नदीनाला, मनावशास्त्र अनि जिवानपद्दतिलाई बुझ्ने इच्छ्या छ।</p> <p>विगतका नेपाल भ्रमणहरूमा जस्तै यसपालि पनि आफ्नो गाउँ अनि अफान्तिहरूकहाँ भ्रमण गरेँ। यसपाली स्याङ्ग्जा, पोखरा अनि चितवन सबैतिर बाबा-मम्मी सँगै नै जाने मौका मिल्यो। बाबाले पारिवारिक भ्रमणका लागि एक हप्ता लामो छुट्टि लिनु भएको थियो। सीमित समय अनि कोरोना महामारीका कारण सार्वजनिक यातायातमा एक्लै गैराख्नुभन्दा घरकै गाडीमा सबैतिरको भेटघाट भ्याउने योजना बन्यो। सर्वप्रथम त हामी कूल पूजामा सरिक हुनका निम्ति हाम्रो गाउँ दिमिक मा पुग्यौँ। आफू जन्मे-हुर्केको ठाउँमा पुग्न पाउँदा मन यसै हर्षित नै थियो। त्यसमा पनि आफूलाई औधी नै माया गर्ने हजुरबुवा अनि हजुरआमाहरूलाई भेट्न पाउँदा खुशीको सीमा थिएन। हाम्रो कूल देवता को स्थान, थान्बारीमा पुग्ने बित्तिकै हामीले तल फाँटमा बर्षाको उन्मादले मत्त भई भेटेसम्मको जमिन, जंगल अनि प्राणीहरुलाई आफूमा समाहित गर्दै कलकल बगिरहेकी काली गंगा लाई अत्यन्त श्रद्धाभावका साथ प्रणाम गर्यौँ। यस श्रद्धाको पछाडी धार्मिक आस्था त छदैं छ तर मेरा निम्ति त्योभन्दा ठुलो कारण हाम्रो जीवनयापन अनि पर्यावरणका निम्ति उनको विशिष्ठ योगदान अनि मेरा बत्सल्यकालीन स्मृतिहरूमा उनको उपस्थिति रहेको छ। धेरै पछि पारिवारिक कार्यक्रममा सहभागी हुने अवसर जुरेको थियो, जुन मेरा लागि निकै सुखद रह्यो। हामीले गाउँमा तीन दिन बितायौं तर यी तीन दिन मा सँगालेका यादहरूले मलाई लामो समयसम्म मातृभूमि बाट टाढा रहेको कर्मभूमिमा संघर्ष गर्न अमूल्य उर्जा दिने छन्। त्यहाँबाट छुटेपछि हामी पोखरा हुदै चितवन पुगी काठमाडौँ फिर्ता भयौँ।</p> <p>पारिवारिक भ्रमण सकेपछि संजयसँग कतै घुम्न जाने कुरा भएको थियो। हामीसँग ३-४ दिनको मात्रै समय थियो तर हामी यौटा अविष्मरणीय भ्रमणमा जान चाहन्थ्यौँ। सगरमाथा क्षेत्रतिर जाने हाम्रो पहिलेदेखिको चाहना थियो, त्यसैले हामीले जहाजबाट लुक्ला पुगी त्यहाँबाट नाम्चेबजारसम्मको पैदलयात्रा तय गर्ने विचार गर्यौं र त्यसका लागि तारतम्य मिलाउनतिर लाग्यौँ। टिकट खोज्ने क्रममा लुक्लाको हवाई सेवा कोभिडका कारण स्थगित गरिएको थाहा भयो त्यसैले बैकल्पिक गन्तव्य खोज्नतर्फ लाग्यौँ। संजयले दामन देखि चन्द्रागिरी सम्म को पैदलयात्रा रमाइलो हुने कुरा गर्यो त्यसैले हामीले यो योजनालाई अगाडी बढायौं। मंगलबारको दिन बाबा ले हामीलाई दामन सम्म पुर्याइदिने एउटा गाडी को व्यवस्था गरिदिनु भयो। करिब साढे ३ बजे गाडी संजयलाइ लिएर मेरो घर मा आइपुग्यो अनि हाम्रो यात्रा सुरु भयो। ड्राइभर दाइ अलिक शान्त सोभावको भएकाले धेरै जस्तो कुरा हामी दुई बिच मै भयो। संजयलाई भोक लागेको हुनाले हामी नौबिसेको एउटा क्याफेमा रोकेर लस्सी खायौँ। नौबिसेबाट हामी त्रिभुवन राजपथतर्फ उकालो लागेपछि निकै घुमाउरो बाटो सुरु भयो। ड्राइभर दाईले पनि बेलुका काठमाडौँ फर्किनु पर्ने भएको हुनाले निकै हाँक्नुभयो। मलाई घुमाउरो बाटोमा यसै पनि रिंगटा लाग्छ अनि त्यसमाथि गाडी को तीव्र गतिले गर्दा मलाई अप्ठ्यारो महसुश भइरहेको थियो। उकाली लागेसँगै मौसम, भूगोल अनि पर्यावरण मा स्पष्ट परिवर्तन देख्न सकिन्थ्यो. अग्ला अग्ला चट्टानी पहाडहरुलाई चिरेर बगिरहेका स-साना खोलाहरु बिशाल ढुंगाहरुले भरिएका थिए. पालुंगको सेरोफेरो मा पुगे संगै तरकारी खेती पनि व्यापक मात्रामा देखिन थल्यो। रोडको छेउछाउमा साना नानी बाबुहरू काँक्रा लगायतक तरकारीहरु बेचिरहेका थिए। विस्तारै विस्तारै उच्च पहाडी वनस्पतिहरू पनि हामीले देख्न थाल्यौँ। हामी दामन को नजिक आइपुग्दा अँध्यारो पनि हुन थाल्यो। हामी कुन होटेलमा बस्ने भन्ने तय नभएको हुनाले हामी बाटोको छेउछाउ होटेलहरू हेर्दै थियौँ। संजयको साथीले एउटा राम्रो होटेल सुझाएको हुनाले हामी त्यो होटेल पत्ता लगाउनतर्फ लाग्यौं। तर दामन काटेर माथि सिमभंज्यांङ्ग सम्म पुग्दासम्म पनि त्यो नभेटिएपछि हामीले गूगलमा चेक गर्यौँ। त्यो त दामनमा नभएर बज्रबराहीमा रहेको थाहा पाएपछि हामी खिस्स पर्दै दामनतर्फ फर्क्यौं। दामनबाट सबैभन्दा नजिकको होटेल सुनगाभा थियो तेसैले हामीले कुनै रिस्क नलिई त्यहिँ बस्ने निधो गर्यौं।</p> <p>हामीले रातको दुई हजार पर्ने कोठा लियौँ र नेपाली खान अर्डर गर्यौं। कोठामा बसेर केहि समय आराम गर्दै हामीले अन्तरंग गफगाफ सुरु गर्यौं। यसरी दुईजना मात्रै छुट्टै बसेर गफ गर्ने मौका मिलेको थिएन त्यसैले हामीले निकै व्यक्तिगत कुराहरू पनि एक अर्कासँग आदानप्रदान गर्यौं। गफ गर्दै जाने क्रममा खाना खाने समय पनि भएछ। हामी तल रेस्टुराँमा गाएर १-१ओटा याप्पल साइडर पिउन लाग्यौँ। सितनको लागि त्यहाँको दाईले आलु-फ्राई ल्याइदिनु भयो। दाइसँग कुरा गर्दै जाने क्रममा उहाले त मेरो साथी निशान रायमाझीलाई राम्रोसँग चिन्नु हुँदो रहेछ। यस्तै सामान्य कुराकानी गर्दागर्दै दाइले खान पनि ल्याइदिनु भयो। त्यहीँको लोकल तरकारीहरू प्रयोग गरेर तयार गरिएको नेपाली खान एकदम मीठो थियो। रहरको दाल, भात, साग, अचार, आलु-भुजिया, काउली को तरकारी अनि पकौडा जस्तै फ्राई गरिएको माछा खुर्सानी निकै नै स्वदिस्ट थियो। टन्न पेट भरि खाएपछि हामी आफ्नो कोठामा गयौँ र भोलिका योजनाबाट उत्साहित हुँदै सुत्यौं।</p> <p>भोलिपल्ट बिहानै उठेर हामी फ्रेश भयौँ अनि बाहिर निस्केर अलिअलि ब्यायाम र ध्यान गर्यौं। हामीले विगतमाझैं यो यात्राको पनि भ्लग बनाउने सोचेर भिडियोहरू पनि रेकर्ड गर्यौं। विहान तुवाँलो लागेको हुनाले वातावरण निकै जादुमय जस्तो देखिन्थ्यो। राजमार्गको बाटो ४५ मिनेटजति हिडिसके पछि हामी दामनको बजारमा आइपुग्यौँ र त्यहाँ को एउटा रेस्टुराँमा नास्ता गर्यौं। त्यहाँको दिदीहरू सँग कुरा गर्दागर्दै समय बितेको पत्तै भएन। हामीले तिर्नुपर्ने ४५० रुपैंया भएपनि मैले ५०० दिँदाखेरि दिदीले निकै अप्ठ्यारो मान्नुभयो। काठमाडौँ भन्दा बाहिर निस्केपछि नेपालमा यस्तो घटनाहरू सामान्यजस्तै लाग्दछन्।</p> <p>नास्ता खाइसकेपछि हामी त्यहाँका स्थानीयहरूसँग बाटोको बारेमा सोद्धै आफ्नो यात्रा लाई अगाडि बढायौं। बाटोमा विभिन्न किसिमका मान्छेहरू भेटिन्थे - धेरै जस्तो तामाङ्ग हरू भेटिए। एकजना व्यक्तिसँग कुरा गरेअनुसार त्यहाँ तामाङ्ग, बिस्ट अनि रायमाझीहरूको धेरै पहिलेदेखि नै बसोबास रहँदै आएको थियो र २००८ साल मा राजमार्ग बनिसके पछि पनि बाहिरका धेरै मनिसरू आएनन्। पहिले पहिले काठमाडौँलाई तराईसम्म जोड्ने यो एकमात्र बाटो थियो र गाडी को चाप पनि निकै हुन्थ्यो, तर आजभोली मुग्लिन को बाटो पायक पर्ने भएको हुनाले यो बाटोको महत्व घटेको छ। हेटौडासम्म त काठमाडौँ बाट सिस्नेरी को बाटो अझै छोटो पर्छ। त्रिभुवन राजपथ र सिस्नेरी को बाटो मकवानपुरको भैसे भन्ने ठाउँमा गएर मिल्छन। यी दुवै बाटोहरू, बिशेष गरेर नयाँ बाटो ठूला ठूला चट्टानहरू फोरेर बनाइएका छन्। नेपालका अरु साना बजारहरूमा जस्तै यो ठाउँका मान्छेहरू सानोतिनो व्यापार (किराना र होटेल), तरकारी खेती अनि बैदेशिक तथा काठमाडौँको रोजगारमा आश्रित छन। होटेलको बिष्ट दाईसँग कुरा गर्दा यस ठाउँमा बिरगंज/हेटौंडाका मान्छेहरू गर्मी छल्न अनि काठमाडौँका केटा-केटी हरु नाइट-आउट का लागि धेरै आउछन् भन्ने कुरा बुझियो। त्यसैले पनि यहाँको अर्थतन्त्रका लागि पर्यटनको बिशेष महत्व रहेको छ।</p> <p>बाटोमा हामी भेटेका जति मनिसरूसँग भलाकुसारी गर्दै अगाडी बढ्यौँ। हामीलाई मोटामोटी कुन दिशामा जाने भन्ने थाहा थियो तर ठ्याक्कै कुन बाटो समात्ने भन्ने चाहिँ थाहा थिएन त्यसैले हामीले गोरेटोपिच्छे नै बाटो सोद्धै हिड्यौं। हाम्रो सुरुवाती योजना दामन बाट मोहनी झरना हुँदै मार्खु निस्किने थियो तर झरना पुग्दा निकै समय लाग्ने अनि हाम्रो गन्तब्य चन्द्रागिरी पनि निकै टाढा भएकोले हामीले झरनाबाट नगएर सिधै जाने बाटो रोज्यौं। दामनबाट १ घन्टाजति हिँडेपछि निकै अप्ठ्यारो बाटो तय गर्नुपर्ने भयो। साँघुरो, चिप्लो अनि ठाडै ओरालो बाटो हामी निकै सावधानीपूर्वक इन्द्रसरोवर ओर्लियौँ। यो नेपालको एकमात्र जलाशययुक्त जलविद्युत परियोजना भएकोले विद्युतीय भार व्यवस्थापनमा यसको बिशेष महत्व रहेको छ। वर्षाको बेला भए पनि जलाशयमा पानि को स्तर तल नै देखिन्थ्यो तर यो आँखाले भ्याएसम्म लामो भएको हुनाले प्रशस्त पानी भण्डारण राखेको कुरामा दुई मत थिएन। नदीको किनारै किनार केहि बेर हिडिसकेपछि हामी एउटा लामो झोलुंगे पूलमा आइपुग्यौँ र त्यहीं बसेर एकछिन आराम सँगै ख्याल-ठट्टा गरेर बस्यौं। केहि बेरमा पुल तरेपछि मार्खु आइपुग्यो। घरहरूका आँगनको बाटो हिड्दै, त्यहाँ को परिवेश अनि जनजीवनलाई नियाल्दै हामी अगाडी बढ्यौँ। चित्लाङ्गतर्फ को उकाली चढ्ने बेलामा एउटा पिकअप आइपुग्यो र कता जाने हो भनी सोध्दा चालक भाइले भेंडाफारम बतायो। हाम्रो यात्रा अझै पनि धेरै नै बाँकी रहेको अनि चित्लाङ्गमा हाम्रो लागि खाना बनिसकेको कुरालाई मनन् गर्दै हामी ३-४ किलोमीटरको बाटो गाडीमा जाने विचार गर्यौं। आफ्नो गन्तब्यमा पुगिसकेपछि हामीले भाइलाई केहि पैसा दिन खोज्यौँ तर ऊ मानेन। अघि बताएझैँ नेपाली समाजको यस्तो चरित्र अझै पनि कायम रहेको देख्दा मनलाई आनन्द मिल्यो।</p> <p>चित्लाङ्गको गोट चिज फारम होम्स्टेमा हाम्रा लागि खाना पाकिरहेको थियो। उक्त फारमक संचालक अशोकजंग ठकुरी काकाले हामीलाई हाम्रो यात्राको बारेमा निरन्तर जानकारी लिईराख्नु भएको थियो। संजय पहिले चित्लाङ्ग जाँदा उहाँसँग चिनजान भएको रहेछ। त्यहाँ पुग्ने बित्तिकै उहाँसँग बातचित हुन लग्यो। स्वागतस्वरूप उहाँले हामीलाई खुर्पानी को वाइन अनि बाख्राको चिज टक्र्याउनु भयो र आफू पनि सँगै बस्नुभयो। उहाँ पहिले राजनीतिज्ञ हुनुहुँदो रहेछ तर आजभोली गैरराजनीतिक रूपमा सामाजिक कार्य मा सक्रिय हुनुहुँदो रहेछ। ५९ सालतिर फ्रान्स र बेल्जियम गई वाइन र चिज बनाउने तालिम लिएर आउनुभएको रहेछ र त्यसपछि त्यहीं फारम खोलेर बस्नु भएको रहेछ। उमेरले ६० जति पुगे पनि उहाँमा एक नौजवानमा भन्दा कम जोश थिएन। उहाँ हामीसँग कुराकानी गर्न निकै लालायित हुनु हुन्थ्यो। एमाले अनि तेस्मा पनि के पी ओलीको पक्षमा वकालत गर्ने उहासँग मेरो ओलीका कर्तुतहरूका बारेमा केहि बादबिवाद पनि भयो। साथसाथै एक बोत्तल वाइन पनि मिलेर सकियो। अनन्त यात्रा को सबैभन्दा कठिन भाग अझै पनि बाकि रहेकोले हामी उहाँसँग बिदा भयौं। जाने बेला मा हामीले ३-३ वटा खुर्पानीको वाइन र १-१ वटा चिज राख्यौ जसले गर्दा हाम्रो झोला निकै भारी हुन पुग्यो। कोभिडको कारणले खासै व्यापार नभएको समयमा ७००० रुपियाँको व्यापार ले उहाँ पनि निकै प्रसन्न हुनुभयो।</p> <p>चित्लाङ्गको मूल सडक लाइ पछ्याउदै अगाडी बढ्दा त्यहाँको रैथाने नेवारी जीवनशैली देख्ने मौका मिल्यो। बुढापाका हरु आफ्नो संस्कृतिक भेषभूषामा सजिएका थिए। कोहि बाख्रा चराउँदै थिए, कोहि भलाकुसारी गर्दै थिए भने महिला हरु घरयसी काम गरिरहेका थिए। केहि अगाडी हिंडेपछि ढुंगेधारा अगाडी केहि केटाकेटि हरू खेलेको देख्यौं र उनीहरू संग हामी पनि गीत बजाएर केहि बेर नाच्यौं। त्यसपछि बाटो ठाडो उकालो थियो। पुरानो गोरेटोलाई ठाउँ ठाउँ मा चिर्दै सँगसँगै घुमाउरो मोटरबाटो पनि अगाडी बढेको थियो। गोरेटो भने निकै चिप्लो थियो - धेरै मानिसहरु ओहोर दोहोर नगरेको थाहा हुन्थ्यो। बाटोमा पनि १ जना बाहेक कोहि बटुवा भेटिएनन्। उकाली चढ्न लगेपछि संजय र म आफ्नो आफ्नो पारामा हिड्न लाग्यौँ। कोसौं टाढा सम्म कुनै मानिसको उपस्थिति थिएन, हामी प्रकृति मा बिल्कुल एक्लै थियौं र एकान्त मा प्राप्त हुने एउटा बिशेष उर्जा हामीलाई प्राप्त भैराखेको थियो। एकान्तले हामीलाई अन्तर्मुखी हुन प्रेरित गरिरहेको थियो. प्रकृति को काख मा त्यसरी ळुट्पुटिने मौका हामी बिरलै पाउछौं, त्यसैले हामी जीवन को आनन्द लिन भुल्ने गर्छौं अनि यस्ता पल हरुले हाम्रो दृष्टिकोण लाई अनंदमायी बाटो मा ल्याउन मद्दत गर्छ। शरीर गलिरहेको थियो भने मस्तिष्क मा उर्जा झन् भरिंदै गइरहको थियो। मन उन्मुक्त भयो भने थकित शरीरमा पनि स्फूर्ति आउछ त्यसैले हामी सबैले आफ्नो मनलाइ सधैँ उर्जाशील राख्न अत्यन्त जरूरी छ। शान्त वातावरणबाट प्राप्त उर्जाको सहायताले हामी कठिन उकालोमा निरन्तर अगाडि बढ्यौँ। अब आइपुग्न लग्यो भन्ने बेलामा गोडा बेसरी दुखिरहेको थियो तर म कुनै आराम नलिई गन्तब्यमा पुग्न दृढ थिएँ। चन्द्रागिरीको टुप्पोमा पुग्दा मेरो स्वश्प्रस्वास निकै तेज भएको थियो, शरीर पसिनाले निथ्रुक्क भएको थियो अनि गोडाले टेक्न पनि गार्हो भैरहेको थियो तर मनमा भने यस्तो जब्बर पहाडको चुचुरोमा पुगेको अथाह सन्तुष्टी अनुभव भैरहेको थियो। त्यहाँबाट हामी गाडीमा चन्द्रागिरी रिसोर्टतर्फ लाग्यौं।</p> <p>रिसोर्ट मौलिक नेपाली शैलीमा आधुनिकता झल्किने खालको शैलीमा बनाइएको थियो। मलाई मौलिक वास्तुकला मन पर्ने भएकोले त्यहाँको भौतिक पूर्वाधारहरूले निकै मन तन्यो. आफ्नो रूममा गइसकेपछि हामी स्विम्मिंग पूल अनि जकूजीको आनन्द लिनतर्फ़ लाग्यौँ। त्यहाँ भेटिएका एकजना संखुवासभाका ब्यापारी दाइसँग केहीबेर भलाकुसारी भयो। दिनभरको पैदलयात्रा पश्चात् निकै भोक लागेको हुनाले हामी भोजन कक्ष्यतिर लाग्यौँ। निकै महँगो भए पनि खाना भने त्यति मिठो भएन तैपनि हामीले टन्न खायौं अनि सुत्नतर्फ लाग्यौं। सुत्ने बेलामा मलाई छेउको कोठामा बजिरहेको हिन्दि गाना अनि जंगलमा मृग कराइरहेको आवाजले निद्रा लाग्न गार्हो भयो तर निदाएपछी चाहिं बिहानसम्म सुतेँ। बिहानपख फेरी स्विम्मिंग पूल मा केहि बेर पौडी खेलेर हामी केबुलकार मार्फत काठमाडौँ फिर्ता भयौं। म सरोज दाईको छोरी को पाश्नीमा सरिक हुन कलंकीमा झरें भने संजय दरबारमार्गतर्फ लाग्यो।</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="personalblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[नेपाल आउँदा संजय सँग कुनै नयाँ ठाउँ मा घुम्न जाने सधैँ मेरो योजना मा पर्ने गर्छ। ऊ मेरो हाई स्कुल देखि को साथी हो र हामी एक अर्का सँग फिरन्ते पारा ले नयाँ ठाउँ मा जान रमाइलो मान्छौँ । बिगतका केहि नेपाल यात्रामा योजना हरु हुँदा हुँदै पनि ऊसँग घुम्न जाने मौका नमिलेको हुनाले हामीले अग्रीम योजना बनाउने काम गर्न छाड्यौँ । वास्तविकतामा परिणत नहुने योजना बुन्दै बस्नु बेकार छ, त्यसैले हामीले सँगै यात्रा गर्ने इच्छ्या लाई प्रबल राख्दै यसलाई भबिष्य को गर्व मै छाडी बस्यौँ। बिगतमा हामीले गरेका मुक्तिनाथ र पूनहिलका यात्राहरू अझै पनि स्मृति मा ताजा छन्, र तिनै स्मृतिले मलाई जीवनभरि यात्रा नै यात्रा गरिरहुँ जस्तो लाग्छ। नेपालका धेरै कुना काप्चा अनि विकट ठाउँहरूको यात्रा संजयले तय गरिसकेको छ। मेरो आजभोली को बसाईं अमेरिकातिर भएको हुनाले मैले नेपालको सोचेजति यात्रा गर्न पाएको छैन, तर मौका मिले सम्म अनि समयले भ्याए सम्म नेपाल आउँदा घुम्ने काममा म सधैं नै इच्छुक हुने गर्छु। भनिन्छ ज्ञान तीन किसिमका हुन्छन - सूतमय, चिन्तामय अनि भावमय। यी तीनमध्ये भावमय ज्ञान सर्वश्रेस्ठ मानिन्छ किनभने कुनै कुरा को देखाई र चिन्तनबाट जति ज्ञान प्राप्त गर्न सकिन्छ त्यो भन्दा धेरै गुणा ज्ञान त्यसको भोगाईबाट प्राप्त हुन्छ। मलाई बाल्यकालदेखि सुन्दै आएका अनि नसुनेका नेपालक दूरदराजका ठाउँहरू पुगेर त्यहाँका मानिस हरु ले गर्ने अनुभूति आफैँ गर्ने धोको छ। हुन त मा विदेशमा लामो समयदेखि बस्दै आएको मान्छे, नेपाल कै अनुभव किन गर्नु पर्यो? अमेरिका, युरोप मा पनि धेरैभन्दा धेरै प्राकृतिक सुन्दरताले युक्त ठाउँहरू छन् भन्ने प्रश्न उठ्न सक्छ। हो, मलाई यी ठाउँहरूको पनि येथेस्ट मात्रमा भ्रमण गर्ने इच्छ्या छ, तर त्यो भन्दा धेरै बढि मलाई आफू यहाँका पर्वत, नदीनाला, मनावशास्त्र अनि जिवानपद्दतिलाई बुझ्ने इच्छ्या छ।]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Synopsis of Atomic Habits by James Clear</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Atomic-Habits-by-James-Clear/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Synopsis of Atomic Habits by James Clear"/><published>2020-12-20T17:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-12-20T17:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Atomic-Habits-by-James-Clear</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Atomic-Habits-by-James-Clear/"><![CDATA[<p>I recently finished reading Atomic Habits by James Clear. I occasionally read books on how other people go about maximizing their potential, for inspiration and ideas. Here, I am attempting to summarize the main ideas that I gathered from this book.</p> <p>What we recognize as self today is an identity that we’ve created over a long period through experience, actions and thoughts. What we are today is a result of what we do daily, aka our habits. Small changes that we make to our habits today can result in compound effects in the long term. If we read ten pages daily, we can finish a book in a month. A few pushups a day can take us a long way in terms of building strength. Taking a short walk everyday can eliminate a long walk to the hospital in the future. Clear points out the story of the professional British bike riders, who had a serious lack of success for nearly 110 years. When they hired Dave Brailsford as the new performance director, he started focusing on making 1 percent improvements in all areas including diet, training, gears and even the coloring of the storage so that dust would be visible. Although nothing significant had changed in one area, the accumulation of these marginal changes led them to an overwhelming success including 5 Tour de France victories and numerous Olympic and Paralympic medals. It’s easy to overlook the importance of tiny changes, but compounded together, they can be the game changer.</p> <p>It’s not difficult to see that we are slave to our habits. A smoker cannot stop smoking despite knowing its impact on his/her health. We all are well aware of eating healthy and doing exercise, yet we fail to do so and end up rather spending our valuable time and money visiting doctors and getting medicines for the ensuing health consequences. Although most of us acknowledge the importance of developing habits that takes us closer to becoming the kind of person we want to be, we fail miserably to various degrees. Only a few seem to break the chain of unwanted habits and create the ones that help them achieve their goals.</p> <p>There are roughly two approaches to breaking undesirable habits and establishing the desirable ones. The first approach is to change the process by winning over our urges. The second approach is based on changing our beliefs, hence our identity, to align with our goals so that the desirable habits become natural to us. I always see a lot of people in the gym at the beginning of the year, but a few weeks into the new year, the number of people goes back to being the same as before. What’s happening is that all these people are pushing themselves to establish a habit by sheer motivation without changing their beliefs. Since motivation is not a perpetual state, after some time, it takes too much mental effort to continue the new habit. This is a classic shortcoming of the first approach. In the second approach, we are not just going to the gym, but we are also making an effort to change our identity into an active, healthy person. Such a person would exercise regularly, so we start going to the gym as a result of the identity. One’s identity can be changed by reflecting and making changes to our beliefs/logic first. The new identity can thus be strengthened by making small changes in that direction. Clear mentions that every time we go to the gym, we become more of an active, healthy person; every time we write a paragraph, we become more of a writer. Once we have enough instances of beating the urge to lie in the couch and consume Netflix to hit the gym, we become more convinced of the new identity. Consequently, we face less resistance to working out because this activity comes out naturally from our newly created identity.</p> <p>One of the common problems that we encounter while trying to change our habits is the lack of clarity of plans. Clear cites a study done on 248 people in Britain in 2001 to build better exercise habits over two weeks. They were divided into three groups and asked to track their exercise activities- the first group was the control group, the second group was given some motivational material, and the third group were asked to develop a clear plan on how they were going to achieve their goal. 91% of the third group exercised at least once a week whereas only 35-38% did so in the first and second groups. Even though we might be incredibly motivated to achieving a specific goal, if we do not structure how we are going to achieve it, it’s easy to give in to laziness, comfort, or another easy way out.</p> <p>The author suggests that such structure can be achieved by associating the new habit we want to establish with something that we already do. For example, telling oneself to fill the planner after the breakfast rather than saying “I’ll fill out my planner in the morning” is easier to execute because we already eat breakfast daily. I have been doing my meditation practice like this for years now. As soon as I come out of the bathroom, I immediately go the corner of the room, where I do my meditation and sit down and get a few minutes in, without trying to think of it as an hour-long activity. Once I settle down and start the process, it gets done without much effort as opposed to previously when I would struggle to make myself sit down, despising the upcoming hour. By having this kind of associative structure, we free our minds of a significant cognitive load also. He suggests making the first two minutes of an activity pleasurable. Once we enter an activity, it’s more likely to end up coming out victorious although it’s not so important when we’ve firmly established a new self-identity that is more in line with our goals.</p> <p>Our surroundings can provide a lot of cues to our behaviors, so Clear also focuses on the importance of carefully designing the environment, conducive to the lifestyle we want to adopt. If we want to eat more fruits, having them placed visibly in a basket on the counter might increase the chances. I remind myself to drink water by always having a bottle of water beside me while I am working. Similarly, the presence of a phone nearby can be of significant distraction to me, so I just put it away in a drawer where I cannot reach when I have to do very focused work. People can also be a tremendous source of influence, so importance of having people around who already follow the lifestyle we want to build cannot be overstated and vice versa. If you want to stop smoking, hanging out with people who frequently smoke definitly doesn’t help.</p> <p>There are many more ideas in the book, but these are the ones that I can recall right now. The gist is to start with “atomic” changes and let these accumulate over years to reap a huge benefit. It seems like a very good book if you are struggling to change your habits and looking for pointers on how to do it. It’s an easy read, so if you are looking to building a reading habit, this might be a very good start.</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="personalblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I recently finished reading Atomic Habits by James Clear. I occasionally read books on how other people go about maximizing their potential, for inspiration and ideas. Here, I am attempting to summarize the main ideas that I gathered from this book.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Consumerism-a worldwide phenomenon</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Consumerism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Consumerism-a worldwide phenomenon"/><published>2020-06-01T17:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-06-01T17:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Consumerism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Consumerism/"><![CDATA[<p>Many of us might recall from our childhood days that buying new stuff was not as easy as it is now. When I tore my pants, my first response was not to immediately log into Amazon and order a new pair; my mom would get a needle from her arsenal of domestic tools and fix the tear. When I needed a new toy, my grandmother would cut a little branch from a tree and make a nice stick for me so that I could pretend I was a policeman. These are just a couple among countless examples of situations that call for a trip to the supermarket nowadays but were fixed differently while many of us were growing up. This difference is very sharp to me because I grew up in an underdeveloped country before moving to the US. While it is true that most of our families make more money than they used to, the rapid rise of consumerism has played a more significant role to alleviate our psychological barrier for buying new stuff. The compulsion for shopping has become obsessive.</p> <p>In most of our minds today, accumulating new and expensive possessions is set as the standard of prosperity and ultimate happiness. However, this is far from reality. Obsessive consumption is not only naturally and financially unsustainable, but also obtrusive to mindfulness and contentment.</p> <p>Consumerism has become a universal centerpiece of the modern lifestyle in the age of globalization. For most of our time in the earth as Homo Sapiens, human settlements have remained fairly isolated. For example, America was unknown to the Europeans until about 500 years ago. Although connected by landmass, large empires like Aztec (in southern North America) and Inca (in South America) were completely oblivious to each other’s existence. In contrast, an idea can easily reach billions of people within a matter of seconds today. This has brought forth numerous positive changes including a wave of democracy. The hegemony of dictators and monarchs fell in the manner of dominos, and democracy, along with capitalism, has taken over. Capitalism prospers when the products produced by private corporations are consumed at a high rate by the free market. Thriving capitalism aspires to make profits by increasing sales. It thus exercises its economic power to grow demand for its products in society, creating a vicious cycle that consolidates consumerism. Our current society seems to have fallen prey to this vicious cycle of capitalism-consumerism with the support of newly achieved global connectivity.</p> <p>There has been an increasingly large number of products in today’s supermarket shelves whose existence raises our eyebrows. Some examples are “cocoa dyno bites with marshmallows” from the cereal aisle, or “sliced mangoes” from the fruits section. When I see them, questions like these arise in my mind- “When did humans start eating chocolate-flavored sugar balls with marshmallows for breakfast instead of some tasty bread, pastry or regular cereals?”. “Since when did we lose our ability to slice our fruits or eat them whole that we have to buy them sliced packaged in a plastic box?”. These might be valid questions; surprisingly, even the most ridiculous of the products find their customers because we are obsessed with purchasing. That’s the entire reason they are being manufactured.</p> <p>Since the corporations benefit by maximizing the consumption of their goods, it’s in their best interest to create more demand to stay on top of the market. Nowadays, they do so by utilizing technology to reach the homes and hearts of people. A hundred years ago, Coca Cola did not exist. Today, coke has been advertised so much that people find a meal incomplete without coke. We did not wander in the plains of Africa smoking cigarettes or JUUL. A large number of people are addicted to these nowadays. Quite frequently, the corporations invent entirely new products with highly questionable utility to penetrate the market. They come up with a solution to our every little problem or the ones that don’t even exist. Although the national economy and consequently the citizens are also benefited by the growth in consumption, only a few owners and shareholders enjoy most of the profits. The limited benefits of consumerism often cloud the harms it is causing to both people and the environment.</p> <p>When we buy a new product, even if it is degradable, it usually comes in plastic packaging with a crisp usual manual. So, it automatically adds to the amount of degradable and non-degradable waste produced by an individual. To put it into perspective, imagine 1 billion people buy a new product and on average produce 0.25 pounds, then it would contribute 250 million pounds to the waste we are already dumping into the earth, a lot of which is non-degradable. Although at an individual level, we are not making that much of a difference to the environment, the difference accumulated over the world population will be quite significant.</p> <p>In addition to being environmentally unsustainable, the modern-day consumerism is not financially sustainable to a large group of people. With the growth of a free-market economy, there is naturally a greater trust in the future, so people enjoy an increase in their credit capacity. We are then systematically influenced by the greedy, capitalistic system into buying more and more things. Most of us are spending the money that we don’t have for the things that we don’t need. We bound to spend the rest of our lives stressing about paying the huge debts that we’ve acquired over the years.</p> <p>Once obsessive consumption sneaks into our lives, the hunger for buying only keeps on growing. This can be satiated only by buying more. The psychological barrier for even simple activities such as dicing fruits, sewing a torn cloth, or walking to the grocery store without our fancy car escalates. Rather than enjoying the process of preparing a meal ourselves, we start buying readymade, packaged food and eat hastily so that we can free up some time to go mindlessly consume something else. It leaves us no time and opportunity for contemplation and mindfulness, which are integral to a content life.</p> <p>We are living in an age when minimalism is seen as austerity and obsessive consumption is considered a sign of prosperity. The capitalistic economic system, built on the pillars of consumerism, has us fully convinced that there’s a void in life that can be filled only by consuming. It has gone so out of control that it has succeeded in creating impossible standards. Men are supposed to buy the diet and exercise products so that they can have the body of Zac Efron, and women are mandated to look white by using the beauty cream called Fair and Lovely (If you look up the ads on YouTube, you’ll immediately see what’s wrong). This certainly means the void created in our minds through aggressive advertisement impossible to fill.</p> <p>It’s time we made it a point to distinguish between the necessary things and the excessive ones. That way, we do not spend our valuable time and resources buying and consuming things that do not significantly contribute to our goals. If we feel the need to obtain something for the short term, we can look for more sustainable options such as borrowing, renting, or buying used products. Resisting obsessive consumerism and embracing minimalism, in my experience, is incredibly conducive to mindfulness. It breaks the cycle of greed and purchase and allows us to enjoy little things in life such as a walk to the grocery store, fixing torn clothes, or drinking unadulterated water.</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="personalblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Many of us might recall from our childhood days that buying new stuff was not as easy as it is now. When I tore my pants, my first response was not to immediately log into Amazon and order a new pair; my mom would get a needle from her arsenal of domestic tools and fix the tear. When I needed a new toy, my grandmother would cut a little branch from a tree and make a nice stick for me so that I could pretend I was a policeman. These are just a couple among countless examples of situations that call for a trip to the supermarket nowadays but were fixed differently while many of us were growing up. This difference is very sharp to me because I grew up in an underdeveloped country before moving to the US. While it is true that most of our families make more money than they used to, the rapid rise of consumerism has played a more significant role to alleviate our psychological barrier for buying new stuff. The compulsion for shopping has become obsessive.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">छुवाछुत् </title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Chhuwachhut/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="छुवाछुत् "/><published>2020-05-29T17:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-29T17:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Chhuwachhut</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Chhuwachhut/"><![CDATA[<p>जसले अफ्ना सन्तानको</p> <p>आङ् नाङ्गै राखी</p> <p>तिम्रो लुगा सिउँछ,</p> <p>जसले आफ्नो बुढो</p> <p>हड्डी खियाई</p> <p>आरनमा तिम्रा औजार पिट्दछ,</p> <p>उसैलाइ भन्छौ तिमी</p> <p>तँ तल्लो जातको अछुत,</p> <p>तैँले छोएको पानी चल्दैन ।</p> <p><br/></p> <p>जसले आफ्ना आफन्तको</p> <p>मलामी छाडेर</p> <p>तिम्रो बिहेमा नौमति बजाउँछ,</p> <p>जसले आफ्नो खुट्टा</p> <p>खाली राखेर पनि</p> <p>तिम्रो जुत्ता सिउँछ,</p> <p>उसैलाई भन्छौ तिमी</p> <p>तँ तल्लो जातको अछुत,</p> <p>तँलाई मेरो घरमा अनुमति छैन ।</p> <p><br/></p> <p>भन्छौ ईश्वरले नै</p> <p>हामीलाई ठूलो</p> <p>र उसलाइ सानो बनाए,</p> <p>उनलाई ठूलो र सानो</p> <p>चाहिएको भए</p> <p>आखिर किन उस्तै बनाए?</p> <p><br/></p> <p>कि त यस्ता ईश्वर,</p> <p>स्ॠस्टिकर्तालाई</p> <p>अयोग्य तिमी मान ।</p> <p>यदि उनलाइ महान्</p> <p>ठान्छौ भने</p> <p>उनको आशय जान ।</p> <p><br/></p> <p>परापूर्वकालदेखि</p> <p>चलिआएको चलन्</p> <p>मान्नुपर्छ भन्छौ।</p> <p>यदि उसको ठाउँमा</p> <p>तिमी भएको भए</p> <p>त्यहि कुरा मान्थ्यौ ?</p> <p><br/></p> <p>तिमी मान्न सक्दैनौ</p> <p>किनकि यो प्रचलन्</p> <p>तिमीले नै बसाएको हो।</p> <p>मन्दिरमा आफ्नै सन्तानलाई</p> <p>बन्देज लगाउने भगवान्</p> <p>तिमिले नै सजाएको हो।</p> <p><br/></p> <p>यस्तो तुच्छ सोचलाई</p> <p>ईश्वरको बाणी</p> <p>ठान्छौ भने अझै पनि,</p> <p>जाऊ पशुलाई छुटाऊ</p> <p>अनि घाँटिमा</p> <p>दाम्लो बाँधेर बस तिमी ।</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="personalblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[जसले अफ्ना सन्तानको]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Breaking up with social media</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Breaking-up-with-social-media/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Breaking up with social media"/><published>2020-05-15T17:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-05-15T17:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Breaking-up-with-social-media</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Breaking-up-with-social-media/"><![CDATA[<p>A millennial who deliberately keeps a distance from social media, the most happening place in today’s world, is seen as an outcast. I changed my allegiance from the mainstream crowd to this group of very few, who often get accused of acting too old for their age, almost three years ago.</p> <p>My decision to temporarily step out of the social media scene came out in response to the looming GRE exam during my junior year of college. As I became mindful of the changes in my lifestyle as a result of this decision, I noticed that I wasn’t any less social than before. Sure, I was not relentlessly devouring infinite information about what’s going on in the lives of people who I’m probably never going to meet in my entire life, but this was not so bad. I was still talking to people who are the most important to me, via other platforms. I was texting and calling people and having more mindful and meaningful conversations with them instead of shooting some random comment at their pictures that probably took me two seconds to cook up. Although the latter gave me the impression that I was in touch with my folks, it didn’t offer me as much satisfaction as I get when I have long conversations with them over phone or text. I became more aware of my social circle and the steps I need to take to foster these relationships. The time to do so was freed up simply by cutting out the time I spent mindlessly scrolling through my Facebook wall.</p> <p>Before you dismiss me as a Thoreau on steroids, I think I need to make my stance clear. I still believe that social media has great power. By using this platform in one’s favor, tremendous growth can be achieved and a lot of people can be helped. My friend Sanjay has been able to gather help for the needy by sharing their stories on his Facebook page with a huge following. He’s a photographer, entrepreneur, and an influencer, so he can reach out to a large audience using his page. For someone like him, I can’t think of a better tool than social media.</p> <p>However, most normal people like me struggle to balance the pros with the cons of social media. We use social media mostly to check how our close ones are doing and what’s going on in the world. We can weed out unnecessary information by unfollowing unnecessary people and pages. Once we do this, we might be tempted to think that our Facebook wall is working entirely in our favor, but this is not the complete story. Social media companies like Facebook hire people to come up with ways to grab our attention for as long as possible. Everything from the appearance, features, the way contents are sorted and suggested has been engineered to decoy us into spending more time using their products. Our valuable time is their source of income, so they don’t hesitate to pour millions of dollars into research. So, the fight to outweigh the pros with the cons is pretty unfair because it’s helpless and nosey by nature human versus a tech giant with billions of dollars in its pocket aspiring to get richer by tempting him to see pictures and videos of his family, friends, and favorite celebrities.</p> <p>The combination of our curious/nosey nature and state of the art attention engineering to pander to this nature can be pretty destructive to our ability to focus. I found myself constantly switching tabs between my course websites and Facebook even while doing my physics homework which was impossible to finish without consistently focused attempts. When I used to deliberately make it a point to abstain from using non-academic websites during the period of my intense work, it brought me uneasiness. I had to remain very deliberate from the entire period of my work because if I let my mind wander away, the next second I’d find myself on the Facebook site. On top of that, I’d be working on things that are objectively very difficult for most of us i.e. physics problems. Getting work done was like fighting an uphill battle.</p> <p>We need to stay focused not just for carrying out mentally demanding tasks but also for as simple of a task like having an informal conversation. To my great despair, I find a lot of people stuck to their phones even while talking to someone else. One of the reasons we’ve succeeded as a species is our ability to have conversations with others, empathize with what they are going through, and show that we do care about their problems. Such nature of ours has helped us in the course of our evolution to form groups with a large number of individuals and consequently have better chances of surviving the brutal natural conditions. With our intelligence, we are no longer subject to the same rules of evolution like that from our time in the caves of Africa. However, we still carry the same instincts. We feel stronger when we have people by our side. We still derive a lot of happiness when we can have a meaningful conversation and influence a lot of people. With the rise of social media in recent decades, the illusion of social association has clouded how much we lagging on the things that are of real importance to us.</p> <p>Another main issue with social media that I recall from my days as an active user is the loss of touch with reality. The pictures one posts in social media are curated to look perfect, and show how successful and intelligent one is. People do not post a hundred mistakes they made rather they only post the one success they’ve had after desperate measures. This is not too hard to understand, but the continuous use of social media makes one lose touch with reality and expect this to be the way how life works. One starts to expect one’s life to be the same as portrayed in social media by others, which is impossible. In my experience, such impossible to meet standard invites nothing but despair, and such a lifestyle can have greater consequences to our well-being. I am not sure if there is any study that confirms social media overuse as the cause of anxiety and depression but I’m aware of a study that shows a correlation between them, which is not to be confused with causation. </p> <p>Having noticed a few positive changes after quitting social media for my GRE exam, I decided to permanently step out and use that time to form relationships and engage in interactions which I value more. Unless my work requires me to rapidly reach out to a large group of people, or some extraordinary circumstances arise, I’ve decided to not go back and live a lifestyle that allows me to be more focused, mindful and satisfied.</p> <p>I was intrigued by Cal Newport’s book “Deep Work”, which had caught my attention while I was visiting my friend Ashim, to think about the changes in my life after quitting social media. I highly recommend his book and blog.</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="personalblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A millennial who deliberately keeps a distance from social media, the most happening place in today’s world, is seen as an outcast. I changed my allegiance from the mainstream crowd to this group of very few, who often get accused of acting too old for their age, almost three years ago.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Quantized Conductance in Gold Wires</title><link href="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Quantized-Conductance-in-Gold-Wires/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Quantized Conductance in Gold Wires"/><published>2020-04-26T22:41:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-04-26T22:41:00+00:00</updated><id>https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Quantized-Conductance-%20in-Gold-Wires</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.gauravgyawali.com/blog/2020/Quantized-Conductance-in-Gold-Wires/"><![CDATA[<p>This is going to be my first Physics related blog post. I just finished proofreading my last ever 6510 lab report. Physics 6510 is a laboratory course that every single graduate student at Cornell Physics department needs to take in order to graduate. If one happens to enter PSB or the Clark hall on a normal day, it is not uncommon to hear some graduate students complain about this course being mandatory or how old and painful the instruments in the lab are. In a typical semester, a student is required to perform three experiments, but (un)fortunately, due to COVID-19, we were able to do just two this time. My second lab was on conductance quantization in the context of Gold wires.</p> <p>Quantization of conductance is a ubiquitous phenomenon in condensed matter physics. In the context of quantum Hall effect, it was first observed by von Klitzing in 1980. This observation gave rise to the application of ideas from topology in condensed matter systems; as a result, a new sub-discipline i.e. topological condensed matter was born. Conductance quantization in such Hall systems is observed only at low temperatures and high magnetic field which is mostly inaccessible to undergraduate/graduate laboratories.</p> <p>In this post, I will discuss the quantization of conductance in the context of point contacts between two Au wires, which was first discovered by Wees et al. in 1988 . In contrast to the quantum Hall systems, this experiment does not require low temperature and high magnetic field making it ideal for studying in a simple laboratory setting. The main concept involved in this experiment is ballistic transport which occurs when the conduction distance is less than the mean free path of the electron so that it can move unimpeded without scattering.</p> <p>If we have a 2-dimensional conductor with length L and width W, the conductance is given by \(G = \sigma \frac{W}{L}\). Based on this formula, decreasing the value of L should cause conductance to grow indefinitely. However, it has been experimentally observed that the measured conductance approaches a limiting value in the ballistic limit. This will be an integral multiple of \(G_0\). Such limiting value will be depend on the width W because it determines the number of transverse modes available for conduction. Assuming periodic boundary conditions, we can estimate the number of modes to be \(2W/\lambda_F\). Thus, the number of modes will increase in discrete steps with the width of the contact.</p> <p>The point of this post is not to subject the readers to my entire lab report, but I’d like to describe the experiment very briefly and share my results. The experimental setup is pretty simple. The heart of the experiment is an apparatus with two Gold wires whose distance can be controlled by turning a screw. After bringing them to an appropriate distance, tapping the apparatus will cause point contacts to be formed or broken between the wires and this will be manifested in the voltage trace measured by an oscilloscope. In some of the traces, we should be able to observe discrete jumps which will ideally correspond to integral multiples of the conductance quantum. I was able to get the following histogram by taking 50 traces with discrete steps out of 1000 traces. My own data was very poor, but I couldn’t take more data due to closure of lab in response to COVID-19. Thanks to professor Anders Ryd for providing me with the data which I think is from a 6510 alumnus.</p> <p>It might be confusing to the reader, how my voltage trace transforms into a conductance value but the voltage can be easily converted to resistance using simple circuit relations, and conductance is just the reciprocal of the resistance. The first useful peak is observed at \(G=G_0\) as expected. Although we expect the second peak at $G=2G_0$, it occurs at \(G=1.86G_0\). The third peak is seen at \(G=3G_0\), and the fourth peak is flatter and occurs before \(G=4G_0\). After the fourth peak, it is hard to discern the peaks so only the steps up to \(G=5G_0\) have been considered. Averaging over the first three distinct peaks, the value of quantized conductance obtained was \((0.98 \pm 0.16)G_0\), where \(G_0\) is the exact value \(7.748091729 \times 10^{-5}~S\).</p> <p>To address the observation of conductance value at non-integer multiples of \(G_0\), it is useful to discuss the validity of the ballistic transport assumption. The provided Au wires are not perfectly pure, and they have accumulated impurities on the surface, so scattering due to impurities is inevitable resulting in non-ballistic contributions. As discussed earlier in the post, ballistic transport occurs when the transport length is smaller than the mean free path. For Au, the mean free path is 37.3 nm \cite{mfp}; thus the nanowire contacts of longer than this length will also contribute to the non-ballistic transport. These issues can be addressed by using a pure sample and cleaning the surface of the wires so that the nanoscale protrusion are removed.</p> <p>Despite not having perfect data, it is remarkable that such magnificent quantum phenomenon can be demonstrated in the lab with a simple experimental setup. Immediately after making this post, I am sending off my report to my instructor, and that shall be the end of 6510 for me unless I fail the course for some inexplicable reasons.</p>]]></content><author><name>Gaurav Gyawali</name></author><category term="scienceblog"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This is going to be my first Physics related blog post. I just finished proofreading my last ever 6510 lab report. Physics 6510 is a laboratory course that every single graduate student at Cornell Physics department needs to take in order to graduate. If one happens to enter PSB or the Clark hall on a normal day, it is not uncommon to hear some graduate students complain about this course being mandatory or how old and painful the instruments in the lab are. In a typical semester, a student is required to perform three experiments, but (un)fortunately, due to COVID-19, we were able to do just two this time. My second lab was on conductance quantization in the context of Gold wires.]]></summary></entry></feed>